A Guide to the Papers of the Cabell Family, 1796-1867
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Cabell Family 1796-1867
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-111-g
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were purchased from Robert L. Self of Wingina, Va., on June 17, 2008.
Scope and Content
The papers of the Cabell and related Bolling families include materials on the War of 1812, a tedious legal case involving Judge Tucker, construction of a mill and a barn, "Soldier's Joy," "Corotoman," "Edgewood," the Female Seminary, Lynchburg, transporting hired slaves to Richmond, the James River and Kanawha Canal Company and company, tobacco prices, a Federal raid near Farmville in 1864, an attempted polygraph purchase, the building of a boat to transport wheat, Joseph C. Cabell's interest in running for office, and a "delicate chemical apparatus," possibly for the University of Virginia.
Of interest are slave censuses from "Bolling Hall" and "Pocahontas," Goochland County, Va.
The collection also contains account books, including one for tobacco sales, 1791-1792 and 1827-1845 that also contains miscellaneous accounts for Thomas Eston Randolph. Account book, ledger, memoranda book, and slave censuses for the Bolling family, 1796-1866, contain plantation records including crop lists, expenses, manager's wages, midwife accounts, slave hires and sales, and rations and clothing allotments for field hands with the note "All lost when freedom came." Estate papers of William C. R. Newburn, William Bolling administrator, 1835-1836, pertain to the sale of Newbern's slaves and include names of slaves, purchasers and prices. There are also lists of taxable property, 1844 and 1862 that mention slaves; a note on the death of Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell and slave girl from diphtheria in 1862; an 1814 marriage indenture of William Newburn and Sarah Randolph, listing slaves; and an Hungarian Fund one dollar note, 1852.
Correspondents and recipients include Robert B. Bolling, William Bolling, Arthur S. Brockenbrough, John Grattan Cabaell, Joseph C. Cabell, Nathaniel F. Cabell, Patrick H. Cabell, Sally F. Cabell, William D. Cabell, William H. Cabell, Dr. George Callaway, John Coalter John Hartwell Cocke, Isaac A. Coles, James Dinsmore, Thomas Dobson, G. W. Featherstonhaugh, Jacques Flouest, William J. Lewis, John Neilson, Reubens Peale, Charles Perros, C. C. Read, James Scruggs, P. G. Tucker, and the Rev. R. H. Wilmer.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Robert B. Bolling to Colonel William Bolling 1843 March 24, April 22, Two letters both concerning the loan of a portrait of a common ancestor for copying. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough to Joseph C. Cabell 1822 May 20, June 4 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Two letters both concerning the terms of agreement with Mr. Peck and Mr. Crawford to do work for Cabell on the same pricing terms as they recently worked at the University of Virginia and to be paid out of the first proceeds of the sale of his wheat.
  - John Grattan Cabell to Joseph C. Cabell 1848 November 29 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Reporting on the buggy made by Mr. Bosher, who appeared willing to sell it for Cabell and make him a light carriage in the spring; also invites his uncle and Aunt Polly to visit his family in Richmond, traveling by packet boat; and notes that his father is engaged in a tedious legal case, that of Judge Tucker, which has been in argument since last week but with only two of eight lawyers having spoken.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1820 June 3 (Box-folder 1:4a)
    Consulting about the purchase of express millstones and securing a workman for the construction of a horse-[drawn?] mill, including a face wheel, a trundle, the hopper, rim, and the crusher.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1820 August 3 (Box-folder 1:4b)
    Has discussed the subject of his thrashing machine and grist mill with Mr. Duncan, but is concerned about the cost; plans on coming to see Cocke's machine before he decides and will also bring Brigg's Report with him.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1820 August 31 (Box-folder 1:4c)
    Asks if he can order Cologne stones for him instead of the others for his mill, has been ill but is getting better, and has had bad luck with the quality of the water in his new well.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1820 September 24 (Box-folder 1:4d)
    Hopes to see him at the meeting at Monticello, asks Cocke to draw him a diagram of a proper plan and proportions of a kitchen fireplace, and a fireplace and a boiler for the washroom at Corotoman in detail so a workman could construct it in his absence, he has also found the fault in his Scotch plow which is working fine.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1822 August 1 (Box-folder 1:4e)
    Recounts his troubles with securing an adequate stonemason for his work, having had to discharge several for drunkenness and asks Cocke if he will send up [Gleeve?]; also writes that the Tuckers are almost ready to move into their new quarters.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1823 April 12 (Box-folder 1:4f)
    Provides details about the construction of his barn and asks for advice on the thickness of the walls and the amount of lime necessary for the proper thickness of the walls, and inquires about where he could get a good wheat fan.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1833 April 10 (Box-folder 1:4g)
    Shares his travel plans from Williamsburg to arrive in Bremo and visit with him.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to Isaac A. Coles 1802 August 28 (Box-folder 5a)
    Makes plans to visit with him on September 5th.
  - Joseph C. Cabell to Isaac A. Coles 1823 April 16 (Box-folder 1:5b)
    Congratulates Coles upon his marriage to Louisa Gertrude Nivison (1795-1824).
  - Patrick H. Cabell to Joseph C. Cabell 1825 August 31 (Box-folder 1:6)
    Explains why he and his brother Samuel have decided to sell their estate, "Soldier's Joy," why he cannot sell off a portion of the entire parcel of land to Joseph without possibly endangering the entire deal with Major Yancey (who has personal animosity for Joseph C. Cabell), and promises one more attempt to see if he can accommodate his wishes.
  - Sally F. Cabell to her father, N.F. Cabell 1862 October 18 (Box-folder 1:6a)
    Writes about her experiences at the Female Seminary, Lynchburg, and her homesickness (Vault).
  - William D. Cabell to "Dear Mother" 1857 October 28 (Box-folder 1:7)
    Assures her that the happiness of his wife, Bettie, was foremost in his mind and that their decision was made together as a matter of Christian duty.
  - William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph C. Cabell 1802 September 17 (Box-folder 1:8a)
    Informs him about the accident of his friend, Isaac Coles, who now will not be able to accompany him to Kentucky should he decide to go there.
  - William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph C. Cabell 1807 May 9 (Box-folder 1:8b)
    Assures him that their mother will not take his absence as an affront but will be pleased to see his wife when most convenient, notifies Joseph about a valuable parcel of land belonging to Hill Carter now available for purchase which lies in an area of the county where he could run for the General Assembly without opposition or collision with a popular candidate as would be the case in Albemarle County, and suggests also a parcel of land offered for sale by John Harvie; he also declines the privilege of packing up the delicate chemical apparatus in his favor.
  - William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph C. Cabell 1811 June 7 (Box-folder 1:8c)
    Asks if he will ride over to "Montevideo" once or twice a year and let him know of anything that requires alteration and states that Roane and Coalter "move on in great harmony."
  - Dr. George Callaway to Joseph C. Cabell 1815 December 27 (Box-folder 1:9)
    Writes concerning the transportation difficulties with getting Cabell's slaves to Richmond and also informs him that the different persons hiring his slaves did not furnish them with the clothing promised and have not yet paid the money for their hire or their physician bills.
  - John Coalter to Joseph C. Cabell 1834 January 11 (Box-folder 1:10a)
    Has not yet received [Robinson's?] report and wishes to have it as soon as possible, cannot spare the time for a "dark and rainy night's" trip in a stagecoach to come into to town.
  - John Coalter to Joseph C. Cabell 1837 January 6 (Box-folder 1:10b)
    Wants to know if he has sold his stock in the James River and Kanawha Company, knows that he is in arrears but not sure how much, but sends a check for $300, and mentions his financial difficulties in losing two successive crops of wheat.
  - Isaac A. Coles to Joseph C. Cabell 1802 September 17 (Box-folder 1:11a)
    Informs Cabell that he has sprained his ankle so badly that all hopes of traveling to Kentucky in the fall has ended and that his trip to Charlottesville did nothing to restore his peace of mind.
  - Isaac A. Coles to Joseph C. Cabell 1813 December 19 (Box-folder 1:11b)
    Has reached Washington two days ago and is waiting to report to the Secretary of War upon his arrival, who he expects will order him to Virginia to complete his [regiment?]; if so, he hopes to stop at Cabell's on his way there; is afraid he may be detailed to be a member of the court martial of General William Hull in Albany; has recovered from the disease which struck him at French Mills; mentions the Battle of Williamsburg, usually called the Battle of Crysler's Farm (Canada); and writes that Colonel Preston, though wounded, was in good condition when he left him.
  - James Dinsmore to Joseph C. Cabell 1826 November 20, Informs him that Neilson is unable to do any work outdoors for some days, so he has sent Mr. [Black?] to do the soldering that he needs. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Thomas Dobson to Joseph C. Cabell 1817 August 26 (Box-folder 1:13)
    Acknowledges payment by a draft from the Bank of the United States for binding Cabell's books.
  - G.W. Featherstonhaugh to Joseph C. Cabell 1836 July 9 (Box-folder 1:14)
    Writes concerning his interest in placing his son in service to Cabell and notifies him about damage on part of the James River and Kanawha Canal about ten miles from Washington, just before the Great Falls.
  - Jacuqes Flouest 1809 December 22 (Box-folder 1:15)
    Merchant in Dieppe and American Vice-Consul to Joseph C. Cabell concerning business, includes a price list for various items, especially tobacco in Virginia and Maryland.
  - William J. Lewis to Joseph C. Cabell 1815 July 8 (Box-folder 1:16)
    Promises to attend to his bank business before he sets out for the springs and regrets he did not see him on the fourth.
  - John Neilson to Joseph C. Cabell 1825 August 1 (Box-folder 1:17)
    Recommends Mr. Widderfield for the work Cabell needs done.
  - John Neilson to Joseph C. Cabell 1825 August 7 (Box-folder 1:18)
    Clarifies the terms he suggested for the hiring of Mr. Widderfield for Cabell's work.
  - Reubens Peale, Museum, Philadelphia, to P.G. Tucker 1811 June 6 (Box-folder 1:19)
    Regrets that they have no polygraph on hand except a used silver one that is not as small as Mr. Jefferson's and that the factory of polygraphs has been discontinued, all referring to his efforts to secure a copying machine for Mr. Cabell.
  - Charles Perrow to Joseph C. Cabell 1835 February 21 (Box-folder 1:20)
    Asks on behalf of Mrs. Morgan if Cabell will check and see if her son, William Morgan, is in the penitentiary as reported.
  - C.C. Read to N.F. Cabell 1864 July 8
    Reports on the results of the latest Yankee raid in the area of Farmville; his mother lost all of her horses but one and a number of slaves, but all returned except for four; Uncle Henry Carrington and his son hid their horses and all their slaves returned; Mr. Grigsby lost all of his horses; Isaac Carrington and his son, Robert, lost all their horses, every pound of meat, sugar, and lard was carried off, along with all wheat and corn and flour, with the plantation land devastated and the slaves carried off; several others lost all their stores except for what was hidden, including [John?] Watkins, B. Green, and Asa Dickerson on his Nottoway plantation; many swept of everything portable including food, clothing, furniture and silver (oversize).
  - James Scruggs to William Bolling 1842 October 27 (Box-folder 1:21)
    Agrees to build him a boat to carry 500 bushels of wheat for two hundred dollars and includes a simple diagram.
  - The Reverend R.H. Wilmer to William Bolling n.y. November 29 (Box-folder 1:22)
    Recalls their friendship and affection and shares his sincere regard for Bolling whom he misses since he is now ministering in Wilmington, North Carolina.
- Series II: Financial and Legal Papers
  - Account Book for "Bolling Island," Goochland County, Virginia 1841-1867, 160 numbered pages. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Kept by Richard M. Bolling, including miscellaneous blacksmith-related accounts for the years 1841-1866 with Boyd Edmunds and Company and with William R. Fleming; beginning in 1866, lists of workers and rations issued for them, pages 128-144, 160; Assessment for the year 1866 on page 95; James River and Kanawha Company; lists of clothing allowances for men, women, girls, and boys, 1856-1857, on pages 152-158, presumably slaves since the comment "All lost when freedom came" is on page 156 with a list of men.
  - Bank Account Book of William Bolling with the Bank of Virginia 1818-1832 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Estate Papers of William C.R. Newburn, William Bolling administrator 1835-1836, 7 items (Box-folder 1:25)
    All pertaining to the sale of slaves belonging to Newburn on January 18, 1836 at Goochland Courthouse, including: receipt from Richmond Enquirer and Pleasants and Abbot advertisement for sale of Negroes (December 23, 1835 and January 7, 1836); receipt for auctioneer Ritchie and Cook (January 18, 1836); an account of the slave sale on January 18, 1836 at the Goochland Courthouse, with slaves listed by name; clerk fee receipt for sale (January 18, 1836); list of slaves sold with the names of the purchasers and price (January 18, 1836); and a receipt for expenses of Edw. S. Gay on behalf of Newburn estate at the Powhatan Court and the use of the Bolling cart and driver in transporting slaves to the sale at Goochland Courthouse (January 20, 1836).
  - Hungarian Fund One Dollar Note, Recipe for Washing, and Empty Envelope 1852, n.d., 3 items (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Ledger of Accounts for the Bolling Family 1816-1844, Folio ledger
    With alphabetical index, including references to slave hires and sales; expenses; purchases; wheat and tobacco crops; medicines; blacksmithing; midwife accounts; plantation manager's wages; shipping and wharf charges; repairs to phaeton and wagons; bookbinding; taxes; also includes alphabetical list of receipts.
  - List of Taxable Property 1844 (Box-folder 1:27)
    Chiefly slaves, who are listed by name; occupation, such as crop hands, domestics, tradesmen; and age.
  - List of Taxable Property 1862 (Box-folder 1:28)
    List of taxable property on a printed form, with number of slaves and shares of stock for Nathaniel F. Cabell; also includes note about the death of his wife, Anne Blaws Cabell, age 50, at Liberty Hall, on February 20, 1862, of diphtheria; the death of a slave girl Lydia, age 12, of diphtheria, in March; and in August the death of a female colored infant Louisa, age 1 year.
  - Marriange Indenture between William Newburn of Chesterfield and Sarah Randolph of Powhatan 1814 January 2 (Box-folder 1:29)
    Lists the slaves owned by each prior to the marriage.
  - Memorandum Book 1796-1803 (Box-folder 1:30)
    Including items furnished to William Robertson and his family and crops delivered from "Bolling Hall" and "Bolling Island."
  - Slave Census for "Bolling Hall," "Bolling Island," and "Cobbs." 1810, 1820 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Slave Census for "Bolling Hall," "Pocahontas," "Bolling Island," and "Wares" 1830
    A total of 162 slaves, with "4 hirelings and one apprentice omitted and old Ben not my property"; slaves listed by name, sex, and age (oversize).
  - Slave Census for "Bolling Hall" 1840
    Slaves listed by name, sex, and age (oversize).
  - Slave Census for "Pocahontas" 1840
  - Slave and Stock Census of Nathaniel F. Cabell and Philip B. Cabell 1861, Slaves listed by name and age. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Tobacco Sales Book for "Bolling Hall," "Pocahontas," and "Bolling Island" plantations, Goochland, Virginia, 1827-1845, and Miscellaneous Accounts, 1791-1792, for Thomas Eston Randolph (1767-1842). 1791-1792; 1827-1845, Bound volume, 84 pages, some blank. (Box-folder 1:33)